So like many great things in life,
this project also starts with a cube.
Just because I'm an old-fashioned person.
I started using Blender when there was no Sculpting,
there was only Box and Poly by Poly Modeling.
What you see me doing here was essentially just adding
Mirror and a Subsurf Modifier, and I got a little bit used
to the Pie Menu editor. Ian was raving about it in the Studio,
I thought, maybe I'll try
to integrate it into my workflow. So what you saw there was
merely just a Pie Menu I made,
to make it easier for me to add a Mirror Modifier and a Subsurf Modifier,
and I hooked it up to the Q key and that was it.
Nothing really fancy and you don't have to use
these kind of Addons to make your workflow faster.
I just wanted to try and see how that works.
Now in the beginning, nothing fancy is happening.
A lot of the tools you see me using here are
fairly commonplace. I'm extruding, pressing down E,
I'm sliding Edge Loops by double pressing G,
every once in a while, I'm adding a new Edge Loop with Ctrl R.
Those keys might also vary on your configuration,
but that's essentially what I'm using currently to block out the shape.
I knew in the beginning that I just wanted
to start this rough with a boxy model
that can be easily extended. I really didn't have any clear idea
how in detail this fish is going to look like.
I had a lot of references from nature, and I knew
I wanted to follow them loosely, because,
nature's amazing and everything.
But for the composition of this image, I have to take
a lot of artistic license as well.
So I tried to be true to the overall feeling, the overall form
of this amazing creature, but then, like the details,
are totally made up.
Now, I'm trying to get the proportions right.
This is probably the most frustrating part.
Because you're not doing anything glamorous right now,
your model essentially looks like garbage.
You just have to have faith, that in the end,
you might be able to come up with something
that's interesting to look at.
I'm just making a copy of the general model here.
Because, next, I'll straight away dive into Sculpt Mode
with Dynamic Topology,
just draw this base mesh. I'm making a copy,
and name everything in the Outliner.
With that copied, I apply all the Modifiers,
then I'll use straight sculpting on the raw polygons.
I also switch to the new sculpting workspace,
which is really awesome to have
these kind of new more defined work spaces.
Because you could customize your workflow in Blender,
but it's also good to have a common starting ground,
especially when you're trying
to communicate ideas to other people, see how they use Blender.
So I'm just starting with the rough Sculpting Work Space.
And then, over the course of this project,
I tried to adjust to its workflow,
and also customize it, so it's not going to stay like that.
The Mattcap is also not going to stay,
and that's just part of the process for me.
So I'm alternating between Draw Brush
using Ctrl to pinch the model in, and the Clay Strip Brush.
Then every once in a while,
I'll use the Crease Brush to indicate some wrinkles.
But this process right now is still fairly loose.
Like I have a rough idea
of how this is going to turn out, but how to get there, I'm not really sure.
I'm also not really a sculpting artist.
So a lot of the practices you see me using here,
if you're a seasoned sculptor, you might laugh at me.
But this is just about me trying trying out
some shapes and some forms. Then hopefully,
I'll try to make this look into something
that's more presentable at the end.
So all very very rough blocking here. The detail and Dynamic Topology
is also not very big currently.
Sooner or later, we'll start
to retopologize this mesh.
So it's not going to matter anyway.
For me, now, it's just about blocking out the big overall shapes.
Then later when we retopologize, we have a clean topology,
we'll use the Multiresolution Modifier,
and then actually worry about all the details,
all the skin creases, all the scales and fins.
So I'm adding a lot of material at once here,
very generous with the Clay Strips Brush.
I wanted to get the right feeling for the mouth of this fish,
mostly 80 to 70% mouth,
and I added that little bit of crease there on the lip,
like right there in the middle,
which makes it more like a carp. Later, you see me removing that.
It was really important for me
to get the mouth correctly.
At least, believable, for this kind of character.
Another important thing is also the ratio versus eyes and face.
So how big are the eyes going to be?
This fish has been popularized quite a bit with Finding Nemo.
In that film,
it's probably a she because
females are bigger than the males.
So the eyes in that film were just huge.
I wanted to get something a little bit more,
like scary on a different level, not alien scary,
but make the eyes small,
make it more like a primal thing,
not like it could be an intelligent things.
That huge blob there in the front aren't
really supposed to be the eyes.
That's more the eye socket.
The iris probably going to be this little dot there.
Now I am just lowering the details size.
It's not adding about detail,
but I get a bit fed Up with all the polygons here.
If you just block out stuff,
you shouldn't worry about seeing polygons, and that kind of stuff,
because it's about the overall shape.
Like said, maybe I also went too quickly
into more detail here. But sometimes I think you need
that kind of inspiration when you're working on something,
especially with this project. I mean,
it's supposed to be more of a fun thing.
Because I spent more than a year on the Spring open movie currently,
I was just doing one thing, which is lighting,
and then managing other people. That's fun,
but I was also missing the immediacy of something like this,
where you just go in and then just bash something out
in a matter of days.
So here, I am with the Crease brush.
That way,
I can define the overall flow of the body shape,
because those creases add some dynamics to the body.
Of course, they should also not be too unbelievable.
They should follow the overall skin texture,
the overall skin alignment, so it's not too much out of place.
This whole project is about lines,
and it's about dynamic flow of lines.
And that was really important,
while I was coming up with this character.
A big part of this was also, for me, some restrain,
because as said, I'm not a seasoned sculptor.
People like Julian here in the Studio,
they sculpt almost every day and they have their workflow,
and they're accustomed to everything.
I'm a total noob at this.
For someone like me, it's very easy to get carried away
with too much detail. And also it's very easy
to introduce unbelievable shapes into my models.
You might get carried away with the Blob Brush.
This makes a little nice blobby thing here
let's try more of that.
At the end of the day, you notice that
looks like a potato. Whereas someone
who's used to a workflow like this,
they do everything with purpose, of course.
So a big part of this, for me, at this point of the project,
is trying to hold myself back,
not going all the way with wrinkle detail.
I'm just trying to make it organic and believable, and hopefully
I'll end up with something that looks aesthetically pleasing to me also.
I'm adding more wrinkle detail in currently.
That's because I'm trying to find the topology of the skin.
Also I knew,
if you check out nature documentary footage,
these types of fish have lots of these tendrils on their bodies.
So I wanted to make sure
that they sit on the skin correctly.
I'm indicating, at this point, a lot of blobs.
Later, I hope
I can add some of these tendrils to those blobs.
So there's a nice flow and continuation.
It's also really interesting how saggy their skin is.
It's not so much, if you look at reference footage,
it's not so much scaly. Actually,
it's more like a saggy lump of of cloth that's floating around in the water.
It's super fascinating.
It seems almost like, especially at skeletons,
the skin is just hanging loosely on their skeletons.
That's what I wanted to try and sell here.
Also, those humps in the back is where the fins are going to extend.
Later, I'm going to add curves to control those fins directly.
Because doing that kind of detail in Sculpting
is a little bit finicky.
In the end, it ends up looking not pleasant.
So that's what
I'm trying to achieve here.
Here, adding a cone for the teeth.
The teeth are fairly simple.
I don't know why I added more detail to them.
I could have just broken up a few to make it a bit more gnarly.
But what I started out with, was a subdivided cone,
and I Link Duplicated that cone
all across the face
to add teeth everywhere. The only variation in those teeth
comes from scaling them on various axis.
So I often just scale around local X axis,
or the local Z axis, to misalign them.
Here, I'm adding a single Mirror Modifier after the Subsurf to each tooth.
I'm using the base body mesh
as the mirror center object. That way,
I can really quickly block out the shapes, by all duplicating the teeth all over.
And using Snapping to the faces
and aligning my object to the underlying snap faces,
I can really quickly block out the teeth.
Again, currently, this is also an exercise of restrain for me,
because this creature lends itself to adding teeth everywhere.
You could go completely crazy
and make this as freaky as possible.
Then again, I've done that in the past with other projects.
With Creature Factory,
there's teeth everywhere.
That gets a little bit like a cliche for me.
So keep it as restrained as possible
and keep a logical alignment to the teeth, and not make them
too crooked and too unrealistic.
Of course, you're screaming at the screen right now,
this is really unrealistic.
Next time, I'll try to exercise more restrain.
Hopefully I'll get something more believable done.
I'll keep my fingers crossed.
Next, the curves I talked about. So I'm adding
a novel Bezier Curve, and I'm adding some depth to it,
to give it some Extrusion. Then, I can shrink the tips down.
That way, I can subdivide them
and the shrinkage will propagate through the subdivisions.
So I'm just shrinkening it, and fattening it,
and then
duplicating the curves all over.  Those curves are both going to be
these long tenderly appendages,
but also serve as the basis for the fins,
also on the back and on the tail end on the sides.
And later, the idea was that,
those curves are going to be integrated into my mesh.
I'll keep the curves around,
later to make Retopology easier.
But then later, I'll rig those and will pose them
in an interesting way, which hopefully fits
with the overall dynamic sense in this image.
That sounds very artistic, I'm sorry.
There're also scale.
They had some points being moved on the X axis.
I just had to quickly scale them on the X axis down to 0,
to make everything aligned on the mirror plane.
Because that's important,
since later, on Retopology,
we're going to to retopologize one side.
I'm struggling a little bit with the reefs apology
along the mirror axis, but
that's just part of the deal for now.
The tail fin is going
to have a little bit thicker lines,
thicker tendrils.
I'm trying to find an interesting flow to them here.
The next thing is the fins on the side.
I'll start out with a copy of the tail fin here,
seemed like a good thing to do.
This is the biggest part.
While the part that impacts the character the most,
the fishing lure of the fish,
I actually had some problems with this.
Here, with curves, it's easy to give them
an interesting dynamic shape, but I had to make this works.
As said, this is only going
to be the base of further sculpting adventures.
If it looks rough right now, that's the idea.
There's also some finy appendage on the chin.
I'm not sure if that's anatomically correct,
but it seemed like a cool thing to do.
And from the chin fin,
I copied the entire object and then I added a Mirror Modifier to it.
Because
the fins on the Y axis,
are directly on the mirror line of this model,
they don't need a Mirror Modifier.
Whereas the fins on the side, they do.
That's why I made a different object,
really quick way of just organizing what gets mirrored,
and what not.
We're starting to get more of an idea
of what this creature is going to look like.
I thought, let's just add a little bit more of those tendrils.
Because later, we can give them
a little bit more interest by making them bioluminescent.
That way, we can direct the viewers' attention much more.
The tendrils
originate from the eyes of the fish are our great opportunity
to lure the viewers' attention towards the eye of the fish,
because there are lines that point directly at it.
Lines that point directly at things are very good in artworks,
because they help directing the viewers' eye to places
where we want them to go.
But of course, those tendrils were a nightmare to retopologize.
Now back to the lure.
I have to realign this thing,
because it would curve inwards and not outwards
if the fish was swimming ahead
at a really fast pace, it would made sense
to have this thing trailing off to the sides.
But I really wanted to curve it inwards.
So later you'll see me realigning that thing.
Now, I'm doing the actual skin flaps between the fins,
and those are just planes which have a Subsurf Modifier.
And then I'm adding a little bit of solidify to those planes.
What I'll do later is,
I'll join everything together. So the curved fin, the curved tendril,
the lure, and all the other objects,
are going to be turned into plane mesh objects.
I'll join those to the main body and then further sculpt on it
using Dynamic Topology. Later,
I will do my best retopologizing it.
That was the quickest way to block out something really fast.
This is the Solidifier with an offset of 0.
The mesh sits right in between the solid part.
That way, I'm able to position the fins right on the mirror axis.
And then the sharp parts are these creases.
I'm not worrying about topology at this point,
I just try to block everything out,
and the creases are really a good way of doing that.
And again, making a duplicate to another object.
Because for the side fins, we're going to add a Mirror Modifier.
I'm not worrying so much about the Retopology
of the.....wait,
that doesn't make any sense, cut that part out.
Here I am positioning the solidified plane inside the fins.
I'm using the Volume Snapping, and with this,
I can precisely snap the vertices off the fins
inside those tendrils here.
Of course, it always needs some realignment here.
But that looks good.
And later, when we join everything and when we smooth everything out,
it's going to be one object anyway.
So we can smooth out the transition between the tendrils
and the skin flaps of the fins.  It's going to seem more like
it's made out of one thing.
Currently, it's a bit hard to sell that idea.
That's the chin fin.
I should make up a better word for this kind of stuff.
I'm just roughly making the fins a size I want.
I just used GG, which is Edge Slide.
The top fin looks a bit strange right now.
I'm trying to mix it with the body in a better way here.
So it will just flow into the head and then into the tail fin.
Now that I have more information in detail on my model,
I can go back to Sculpting.
Later when we join everything, I can give it the final touches.
As I said, Sculpting is not going to be the final step.
I don't even dare to do detailing at this point.
Because when you're detailing in Dynamic Topology,
you have to be very super fine detailed.
Otherwise, if you're baking a Displacement Map from that,
it gets tessellated.
So I'm not a huge fan of baking Displacement Maps from Dynamic Topology meshes.
That's why I decided to go
with Multiresolution in the end.
This is the said realignment of the lure.
I'm also making it a little bit shorter.
Probably in practice in the end,
it could be even shorter to make it easier
for the final image composition. Because having a lot of
these tendrily objects in a frame can make it very busy.
In the end, I had a really hard time managing all these lines.
The eyes,
just a simple sphere. I'm scaling down on one axis
and then assigning a Mirror Modifier to it.
There's going to be some detailed modeling later.
But this is fine for now,
to give me more as a sense of the character,
also going to help sculpting the eye socket.
I'm trying a little bit of eyelids here.
But with fish, you really don't want to give them eyelids.
Except when you're making an animated film with cute and cuddly fishes.
But if you want to make something look scary,
you don't give it eyelids.
Some troubles with Extrusion.
Now,
we're pretty far into the overall proportions of this creature.
So I'll try to join everything together.
I'm happy
with the overall ratio of fins versus body, the face,
looks fine to me. I mean I could go on forever with this,
but there was also a limited time frame.
Now I need to convert all the curves to meshes first.
Then I have to apply the Modifiers of those skin flaps for the fins.
In order for that to happen,
I need to organize myself a little bit better, and name things,
and move everything to the proper collection.
I use the Boo Tool Addon to Boolean things together, which is super handy.
It's one of the default Addons.
It's not enabled by default, but you can enable it,
and it makes Booleaning things together, really quickly,
much faster.
So I've joined the fins together and here
I'm testing out if it's possible to do what I want with this.
I had no clue.
So I smooth out the transitions between the skin,
the body, and the skin of the fins.
That helps thickening out the basis of the fins a little bit,
before I add more of those tendrils to it.
Right now, this is pure exploration
to see if I can do what I want to do with this.
Still just smoothing out, and next,
I'm adding the tendrils, the curves,
and converting all the curves into Mesh Objects,
seems like a good thing to do.
The reason why I use curved for modeling and not straight meshes
is because
you can vary the detail level as you're working on it more easily.
Sometimes, of course, curves give you more problems,
especially on the ends, because they're not joined together.
So I just select
all the open edges here, and I'm joining everything together.
I have to be super careful at the ends
to make sure the tips are all joined together.
Because by default, Blender doesn't do that.
Even if you're shrinking down a curve to 0, it doesn't join something together.
You have to do that manually at the end,
that's what I'm doing here.
Of course, there's also a little bit of a shortcut to it.
But I'll do that in the second run here.
I also have to say I'm sorry that I customized my Merge menu.
I actually turned it into a Pie Menu,
which is just quickly,
I just wrote myself an Addon, that's not a big deal.
But I like it much better
because you can flick into a certain direction
and emerge that way more intuitively.
I did another tech check for
Manifold Edges and Vertices,
just to see if I missed anything.
Now the faster way to do this is,
here, I'm turning the other tendrils into meshes.
The faster way to do that is search for Manifolds right from the start,
because then Blender will select them.
That's why I'm doing here.
I'm searching for Selecting Non Manifolds, and then I press F.
Pressing F will just make faces, they're not really nice faces,
they are Ngons.
That doesn't really matter for the Boolean process.
That way,
the tips and the bases of those tendrils are joined together.
Then in the end, I did a Merge by Distance
which will finally fuse the tips together. Just to be sure.
It helps to do something twice,
so just check if they actually happened.
Joining everything together.
Just using Boolean Union and I'm actually joining everything together,
I'm not creating Boolean Modifiers.
I'm stupidly and flatly bashing
all the stuff together right now.
Again, filling holes, making everything manifold,
and then joining everything together.
Now, more fun, more sculpting fun can happen,
because now I have a continuous mesh and I can make sure that
the tendrils fuse into the body in a nicer way.
And of course,
I was probably getting carried away too quickly,
and I didn't pay attention to the Subdivision Level here,
because those created quite a lot of artifacts on the curves,
or the tendrils, as I call them.
For the next project, I'll just keep that in mind.
I'm super quickly smoothing out things.
I'm using the Blob Brush to add more volumes
to those tendrils and those lures to make it more organic.
These are some of the artifacts I talked about.
Now, it's really just about making
the skin flaps of the fins feel a little bit more real,
and
less of straight lines.
Again, another artifact. But those are going to go away
once I do Retopology.
While I'm sculpting, I found that it's a good practice
to switch Mattcap every once in a while, to get a fresh eye on things.
That's what I'm doing here. Sometimes a Mattcap
can give you interesting surface detail,
that's more inspiring for you to work with.
Which is a good thing because on a project like this,
you work on it for a long time,
keep yourself inspired is very important.
Especially if you're not working with a team. If you have colleagues,
or friends whom you can show the stuff,
don't hesitate to do that.
I got a lot of great help from people just dropping by my desk
and giving me notes about this. Especially for the final image composition,
I learned a lot of stuff, and I'm really happy that
I know work with people who you can just poke every day,
and in the end, your artwork is going to look better.
So the final run of merging the eyebrow tendrils,
would called them eyelashes, into the body. Those were a bit tricky,
because I reposition them in the Sculpting process.
That way I had some problems retopologizing them.
So I had to join the curves back
to my retopologized mesh later on. Well, I'll mention that again
when I get to it.
This is almost the end. I'm doing some wrinkles here,
but that's really details which we're going to add in later.
Right now, we have the overall shapes in there,
the overall lines that the topology has to follow.
Then we can just dive into Retopology right away,
and later, have more time for Sculpting details
and adding a little bit more interest.